<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The thinges vvhich happened vpon the Prince of Parmas retire since the 20. of Nouembre, till the 27. of the same moneth With the newes from dauphine. Published by authority.</title>
            <title>Ce qui est advenu en la retraicte du duc de Parme dupuis le 20 Novembre jusques au 27. English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A16443</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 336</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115280</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850499</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850499</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15707</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A16443)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15707)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1537:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The thinges vvhich happened vpon the Prince of Parmas retire since the 20. of Nouembre, till the 27. of the same moneth With the newes from dauphine. Published by authority.</title>
                  <title>Ce qui est advenu en la retraicte du duc de Parme dupuis le 20 Novembre jusques au 27. English.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5, [1], 5-19, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Wolfe, for Andrew White, and are to be sold at his shop at the Royall Exchange, ouer against the conduit in Cornehill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Page following the first page 5 is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Peterborough Cathedral. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Alessandro Farnese, --  Duke of Parma, 1545-1592.</term>
               <term>Lesdiguiéres, François de Bonne, --  duc de, 1543-1626.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Wars of the Huguenots, 1562-1598 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15707:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15707:1"/>
            <p>The thinges which <hi>hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened vpon the Prince of Parmas</hi> retire ſince the 20. of Nouembre, till the 27. of the ſame Moneth.</p>
            <p>With the newes from Dauphine.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed by authority.</p>
            <p>LONDON <hi>Printed by</hi> Iohn Wolfe, <hi>for</hi> Andrew White, <hi>and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the Royall Exchange, ouer againſt the conduit in Cornehill,</hi> 1590.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="history">
            <pb facs="tcp:15707:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15707:2"/>
            <head>The thinges vvhich <hi>hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened vpon the Prince of Parmas</hi> retire ſince the 20. of Nouembre, till the 27. of the ſame Moneth.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He <hi>20.</hi> of Nouembre ſhe king being departed from <hi>Coeuures</hi> to purſue the Prince of <hi>Parma</hi> and the Duke <hi>de Mayne,</hi> who were together: met in a great playne a companie of naturall Spaniardes, which he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfited in the ſight of the Duke <hi>de Mayne,</hi> where the Baron <hi>du Fort</hi> was hurt with a muſket ſhot.</p>
            <p>Since the <hi>25.</hi> of the ſaid moneth, his Maieſty remoued from <hi>Feres</hi> in <hi>Tartenois,</hi> vpon notice that was geuen him of the Prince of <hi>Parmas</hi> departing from <hi>Fiſmes,</hi> a ſmall towne, where the riuer of <hi>Voeſte</hi> paſſeth thorowe, and marched directly after him, accompanied with eight hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth launciers, and as many carbines, commanding the Baron of <hi>Biron</hi> to take <hi>15.</hi> light horſemen, and ſend them for ſpies to get the watch word. In the meane while hée went into a wood lying vpon the right hand, accompanied onely with <hi>25.</hi> horſes. The ſpies of the ſaid baron of <hi>Biron</hi> brought newes, that the enemy was departed from a ſmal village called <hi>Bazoge,</hi> and that they marched towardes <hi>Pontauers</hi> where the riuer of <hi>eſne</hi> paſſeth thorow. Vpon the ſame time the king came into the ſaid village, where he found none but certaine farmers and huſbandmen armed,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15707:3"/>and readie for to fight in his Maieſties behalfe. The king ſent <hi>Monſieur de Fronterac, Chicot,</hi> and <hi>Dauerus</hi> to eſpie vpon <hi>S. Martins</hi> mount if the enimy had no am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſhes at the foote of the hill, but they ſaw them plainely in an open plaine, their faces turned towardes <hi>Pontauers.</hi> His Maieſty paſſed the riuer of <hi>Voeſle</hi> in the foreſaid vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, and commanded <hi>Monſieur de la Noue</hi> to march in all haſt with his forces towardes <hi>Pontarſy,</hi> to ſtop the paſſage of the riuer of <hi>Fſne,</hi> when in the meane while hee went to purſue the enemy. And being ſomewhat forwarde in the plaine, eſpied ſome horſes to follow him, with foure regiments of footemen, who arriued in the ſaid towne of <hi>Fiſmes,</hi> and were appointed to conuoye the tronkes and bagage. If his Maieſtie had bene ſupported with fiue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth horſemen more then he was, he would haue ſet vpon them: but ſearing that his men would linger about the ſtuffe and carriage, it made him not to venture, but mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched a great league within the plaine, ſending the ſaid baron <hi>de Biron</hi> with <hi>25.</hi> lanciers before his cornet of light horſe. Commanded alſo <hi>Monſieur de la Noue</hi> to ſend him ten ſoldiours out of euery companie, and to lodge and refreſh the reſt of the armie, which he did. Then his maieſtie made fiue ſmall ſquadrons of horſemen of <hi>50.</hi> or <hi>60.</hi> horſes in euery troupe. The carbines of the enimy began to draw towardes the baron of <hi>Biron,</hi> whom his Maieſtie did back a farre of, accompanied with the Lord <hi>Alfonze Lorſe,</hi> and at the ſame time the ſaid baron charged the earbines, in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much that of them eight or nine were ſlaine vpon the place.</p>
            <p>The king being ioyned with him, the ſaid Lord <hi>Alfonze</hi> ſhewed unto his highnes the Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> who wore at that time a flat crownd hat, a great ruffe, and a ſhort mandilian furde, and was mounted vpon a gray horſe, lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15707:3"/>his hand vpon his ſword for to make his men to retire, and in a brauerie making his horſe to leape ſix or ſeuen times, the king doing the like of his ſide, being diſtant one from an other not much more then <hi>100.</hi> paces. His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie dougting that this refrait of the enimie, was onelys but to draw him further in, and ſo to compaſſe him with the whole bodie of their armie, at the arriuall of <hi>Monſieur de la Noue,</hi> who tolde him that he had ſéene vnto his thinking, all the enimies cauallerie and infanterie in bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile aray, commanded preſently a retrait, and not thinking that the retire would fall ſo long, was forced to remaine foure houres in battaile aray before the enimy, who came armed vnto him. Whereupon he left to backe him, the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron of <hi>Biron</hi> with his troupe of light horſemen, conducted by <hi>Monſieur de Sandall,</hi> who had left Captaine <hi>Brouſt</hi> and two companies of light horſe twenty paces behinde him, to keepe the carbines in breath. An indiſcrete ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diour and one of his Maieſties troupes being fallen into the handes of the enimies light horſemen, began to crie aloude for aide, three went to helpe him, where captaine <hi>Brouſt</hi> receiued a ſhot in his left eie, wherewith hee fell dead from his horſe. Hereupon the ſaid baron <hi>de Biron</hi> returned di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly towardes the enimie, and cauſing the dead bodie to be laid vpon a horſe, and to be carried vnto the towne of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gauall,</hi> made a ferme ſtanding vpon the top of the hill, from the which he could not come downe into the ſaid village, incloſed with a lowe bricke wall, but through a ſtraight and narrow way. His Maieſtie thinking that the baron of <hi>Biron</hi> was inda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gered, would haue commanded <hi>Monſieur de Sandall</hi> to giue a charge with his light horſes, but ere long notice was giuen how he had preuented the enimie, and that his backe forces being ioyned with him, had toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther purſued the enimie more then a thouſand paces in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15707:4"/>playne. The king knowing that beſides the narrownes of the way, where he was forced to paſſe through, his enimies did vrge and preſſe him verie néere, thought it better to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard certaine carbins that were with him, then to venture and caſt away his Nobilitie, cauſed therefore two compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, the one of <hi>S. Denis,</hi> and the other of <hi>S. Feliz,</hi> to light, and by theſe meanes there began a very hote ſkirmiſh. In the meane while all his Maieſties caualerie retired, the carbines alſo diſmounted and came furiouſly running from the hill into the ſaid towne of <hi>Longauall</hi> where his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie was. The ſhot alſo retired thither, but Capitaine <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix</hi> in the retrait was ſlaine with one of his ſmall ſhot, and one of his Maieſties light horſemen, and foure or fiue horſes of the deadmens. The ſaid hargebuſiers had not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding yet leaſure enough to bring the Captaine a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, drawing him by the legges into the village, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they ſhut the gates vpon the enimie, who with their ſwordes gaue many blowes vpon the gates, and through the flites there of with their pickes and launces. Our ſhot in the meane time kilde a great nomber of them through the loop holes that were in the wall, which when the eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie did ſée, he went to aſſault the place at an other ſide, in hope to come within the village, where he found the gates ſhut, but hauing gotten meanes to open it by the helpe of a countrey man, ſixe of them entred, where preſently they met Captaine <hi>Bonomouer,</hi> Captaine <hi>S. Denis,</hi> an a ſhot. The Captaine <hi>Bonomouer</hi> went directly towards them, and hauing throwen one downe with a ſhort picke, cauſed the ſaid ſhot to diſcharge his piece, who kilde an other. The reſt ſeeing this, they abandoned the place againe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the ſaid <hi>S. Denis</hi> ſhut the gates. The hargebuſiers tooke their horſes and folowed the king, who leſt the town, where into the enimie preſently entred. Betwéene this vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:15707:4"/>and the towne of <hi>Pontarſy</hi> there lyeth a woode, at the ſide whereof his Maieſtie placed his lanciers in battaile a, ray, to make thir ſtanding ſure, and ſo paſſing the wood, got the towne of <hi>Pontarſy,</hi> where all his troupes paſſed the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. The enimie went directly out of the village, ſtanding ſtill a while by the way, for feare of ambuſh of ſhot, that might be lodged in the wood, but at laſt they paſſed through it, and met with the baron of <hi>Biron,</hi> who gaue them a charge, and ſlewe fiue and twentie or thirtie of them. His Maieſtie cauſed Captaine <hi>Langemis</hi> company to light, who ſaluted the enimy with ſuch a value of ſhot, that they kilde a great nomber of them, and thus they retired to the towne againe and paſſed the riuer. The duke of <hi>Parma</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan likewiſe to retire, encamping him all night there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, fearing an alarum, thinking that <hi>Monſieur de Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers</hi> came behind him. Next morning <hi>25.</hi> or <hi>30.</hi> of the eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies carbines hauing loſt their way, came before the ſaide towne, enquiring for the Prince of <hi>Parmas</hi> quarter: and being ſuffered to enter into the town, the inhabitants ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of hauing diſarmed them, threw them from the bridge into the water and drowned them. His Maieſtie ioyned with <hi>Monſieur de Neuers</hi> the <hi>27.</hi> of the ſaid moneth, as alſo with <hi>Guiret</hi> and <hi>Parauall,</hi> who brought him certaine troupes verie well appointed, with the which they parting the ſaid day from the Caſtle of <hi>Niſy,</hi> perſued the enimie, marching towards <hi>Larbre de Suyſe:</hi> The ſurceſſe of which purſute, you ſhall fourth with receiue.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="news">
            <pb facs="tcp:15707:5"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:15707:5"/>
            <head>Nevves from Daulphine.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Lorde <hi>Diguires</hi> hauing receiued the Kings commaundement by two let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of his Maieſty to warre againſt the Duke of <hi>Sauoy,</hi> thought it good to delay no longer the execution of his will. But vpon the receipt of his Letters, which was about the latter ende of Maie (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing delayed his purpoſe vntill then, but onely for the lets and hinderances hée had in <hi>Prouence</hi> which was aſſaulted in diuers places by the leagers of <hi>Sauoy, Lionnois,</hi> and <hi>Daulphine</hi>) purpoſed to put in all haſte the Kings com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manndement in execution.</p>
            <p>This deliberation was yet ſtayed for the aide which he in perſon was forced to giue to the Lord de la <hi>Valette,</hi> in the moneth of Iune and Iuly, which were almoſt who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpent in the affaires of <hi>Prouence,</hi> where they had ſo good a ſucceſſe, that the enemy (hauing refuſed the combate, and loſt the field) abandoned in token of his cowardneſſe the Townes and Caſtels of <hi>Peruis, Pumichet, Vallanſele, Montaignac, Soluiers, Pignauers,</hi> and <hi>Lorgis,</hi> ſome of them brought vnto the Kings obedience by force, and ſome by compoſition.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:15707:6"/>
            <p> During this abſence, the Captaine la <hi>Cazette,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Maieſties ſubiect, but yet affectionated vnto the Duke of <hi>Sauoy,</hi> compounded with the Duke vpon the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the Townes and Caſtels of <hi>Briancon,</hi> and <hi>Eſsiles,</hi> kept by thoſe of the Neutralles, and hauing receiued com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to that ende, to leauie ſouldiours, expected the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riuall of foure and twentie Spaniſh companies for to bring his enterpriſe the more eaſier to effect by their aide and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce.</p>
            <p>The Lorde <hi>Deguiſires</hi> informed of long time of his practizes, and foreſéeing the importance of that loſſe, which ſhould hinder and ſhut vp the paſſage of the Artillery and French armie, and leaue no way to come by any meanes in <hi>Piemont,</hi> practiſed ſo purpoſely with the chiefe inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the ballies: that by their means the houſe of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zette</hi> was blowen vp, and he ſlaine, the fiftéenth day of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And ſo the Duke was there for that time preuented of his purpoſe.</p>
            <p>This newes being brought vnto the Lorde <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſires,</hi> it cauſed him to turne backe into <hi>Daulphine,</hi> and to march in all haſte towardes <hi>d'Ambrum,</hi> where the deputies of the ſaide vallies did méete him, who (after they had declared vnto him the treaſons of <hi>Cazette,</hi> by the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers which were founde in his houſe) bounde themſelues by oathe to be faithfull vnto the King: and ſo they were ſent backe againe, to bring the people that had ſent them more affectionated vnto his Maieſties ſeruice and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:15707:6"/>
            <p> In the meane while the ſaide Lorde <hi>Deguiſires</hi> bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aduertiſed of the wauering, which the ſaid death, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarie yéelding of that people, and the Towne of <hi>Brian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con</hi> did cauſe, and knowing alſo, that thoſe which were of the Kings ſide within the Towne, beganne to be incoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, cauſed foure Cannons to be drawen and brought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that place. Which when they were planted, and a breach made, the enemy did parlée, in ſo much, that the Towne and Caſtell thereof were rendred at the laſt, being the ſixtéenth day of the moneth of Auguſt, by <hi>Clauiſon,</hi> who was appointed Gouernour by the Duke de <hi>Maine</hi> of that place.</p>
            <p>From thence the Lorde <hi>Deguiſiers</hi> went to <hi>Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geure,</hi> to take <hi>Eſsiles</hi> vpon a contract which he had made long before with the Gouernour thereof. And ſéeing that this bargaine was made but in wordes onely, and that he was not ſufficiently prouided to force the ſaide place, and that the Lorde de la <hi>Valette</hi> did daily ſoſticite him to geue aide to Saint <hi>Maximine,</hi> beſéeged by <hi>Martiningo,</hi> hée was contented to take, for that time, the oathes onely of the communaltie, who ſhewed themſelues greately affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionated vnto the Kings ſeruice.</p>
            <p>After this hée tooke his way towardes <hi>Prouence,</hi> and lodged the fiftéenth day of Auguſt neare-vnto <hi>Barcelone-Salines</hi> an olde Spaniſh Captaine, being chiefe Colonell of the light horſemen of <hi>Piemont,</hi> during the Kinges warres, departed at that time from <hi>Barcelone,</hi> whereof kée was Gouernour vnder the Duke, and aſſaulted one quarter where one companie of the Infanterie of <hi>Boyſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:15707:7"/>and twelue launces of the Lorde <hi>Brickmorte</hi> were lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, who receiued them ſo valiantly, by the ayde of twoo other companies of footemen that came running thither in all haſte vppon the noyſe they hearde, that <hi>Salines</hi> lefte ſixe ſcore of his men dead, and thirtie Spaniardes taken, ſauing himſelfe but with ſixe other. <hi>Voluant</hi> Capitaine of the Dukes guarde was there alſo taken, and hurte, whereof he died wythin a day after, receiuing by his death a iuſt rewarde and puniſhment according vnto his deſerts, becauſe he had ſolde vnto the deceaſed Duke of <hi>Sauoy,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the death of the Marſhall de <hi>Bellegarde,</hi> the Towne and Caſtell of <hi>Cramanolle,</hi> where he and his ſather were Gouernours of for the King.</p>
            <p>The nexte day following, being the ſixtéenth day of Auguſt, the ſaide Lorde tooke by compoſition the Caſtell of <hi>Roſolez,</hi> which is the Dukes, and had there in garriſon two companies of footemen that were permitted to departe with their armour, but lefte their colours behinde.</p>
            <p>After this exploite, continuing his waie, hée came into <hi>Prouence</hi> ſo fitly for thoſe of Saint <hi>Maximine,</hi> that <hi>Martiningo</hi> aduertiſed of his comming (his army béeing very weake and diſordered) remooued his ſiege. And the Lorde <hi>Diguiſiers</hi> now entered in the country, to the end, that hée might there leaue ſome token of his comming, cauſed thrée Cannons to be brought before the Caſtell of <hi>Barles</hi> to batter it. And after a ſiege of eight dayes tooke it at his owne diſcretion the laſt day of Auguſt.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:15707:7"/>
            <p> During theſe iourneys the Duke of <hi>Sauoy,</hi> being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companed with thrée thouſand footemen or there-aboutes, and foure hundreth light Horſemen came to beſiege and batter with thrée Cannons, a Church called, Saint <hi>Paules,</hi> which the ſaide Lorde <hi>Diguiſiers</hi> had but in paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing by fortiffed, ſcituated in the dominion of the ſaid Duke, foure or fiue leagues from <hi>Ambrum,</hi> and tooke it by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, the garriſon thereof going away with their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, coulours, and drumme in battaile aray, the verie ſame day that <hi>Barles</hi> was taken.</p>
            <p>The ſame day alſo the ſawe Lorde <hi>Diguiſiers</hi> béeing aduertiſed of the ſéege of Saint <hi>Paule,</hi> Marched in all haſte and diligence to ſuccour it, with intent to offer the Duke a battaile, vſing to that ende ſo great a celeritie, that the third day of September hée lodged in <hi>Varret,</hi> thrée leagues from his Highneſſe, whe béeing diſmayed at his ſodaine and vnlooked for arriuall, tooke the paines to retire in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the ſame night from the mountaine of <hi>Larche,</hi> and marched all that night with Linkes, béeing the nerte day followed by his owne forces, whereof ſome in the rere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde were ſlaine and taken, and amongeſt other, <hi>Don Pedro</hi> de <hi>Vegiers</hi> a Spaniard, and archer of the Dukes ſooteguarde was taken.</p>
            <p>The nexte day following, which was the firte day of the ſawe moneth, the Lorde <hi>Diguiſiers</hi> was reſolutely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined to force and aſſault Saint <hi>Paule</hi> againe, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he had not his Cannons ready at hand, yet did hée lay ſéege vnto it, aſſaulting it with handiblowes, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tting blowne vp the gates, and made a breach cauſed twoo
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15707:8"/>hundreth of the souldfours that were within it, to be put to the Sworde taking none priſoner, but the Captaine de <hi>Strata,</hi> gouernour of the ſaid place, and his Enſigne ral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Hercules Couero</hi> of <hi>Millan.</hi> This Forte remained but foure dayes in the ennemies hande, and was taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in a ſkirmiſh which continued thrée houres, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, of the Kings ſide, but one Captame was flaine, called <hi>Bolleuene,</hi> and ſome fewe Souleiours hurte, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that the Forte had Flanquers and Ditches round about it.</p>
            <p>At the ſame time that the Duke did batter Saint <hi>Paule,</hi> he had cauſed his army with ſome parte of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Sauoy</hi> and <hi>Piemont</hi> to march towardes the valley of <hi>Eſsiles,</hi> hoping by his forces which were of foure thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand footemen, and thrée humdeth horſe, to ſake and ſpoils all the Countrie of <hi>Briancon,</hi> to batter <hi>Guileſter,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer-runne <hi>Lambriuois.</hi> But the lorde <hi>Deguiſiers</hi> bée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hereof infourmed, and deſirous fo diſapporint the Duke of his purpoſe, preſently after the taking of Saint <hi>Paule,</hi> which he racrd vnto the grounde, tooke his tourney to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes <hi>Briancon,</hi> and knowing that the ennemie, who was lodged in <hi>Cheumont,</hi> made preparation to force the paſſage of <hi>Selte,</hi> kopt and fortified by the inhabitants of the valleis, ſent thither <hi>Monſieur</hi> de <hi>Morges</hi> his nephew with his company of fiftie horſemen, and two Enſignes of footement, and arriuing thither, vppon the point and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant that they were in a ſkirmiſh, he lighted with his men, and ſetting them in battell aray, incouraged ſo much the heartes of euery man, that the ennemy (affaulting in thrée ſundry places the Forte and Bulwarks with fiftéene hundreth footemen, and foure ſcore or a hundreth men of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:15707:8"/>armes) was repulſed, leauing ſixe ſcore of his men dead vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the place: which happened vpon the ninth day of Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember.</p>
            <p>The thirtéenth day of the ſame moneth the lorde <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſires</hi> arriued in <hi>Douley,</hi> thrée leagues from <hi>Eſsiles,</hi> where newes was brought him, that the Duke hauing ſent one parte of his forces vnto <hi>Monſieur</hi> de <hi>Sonnes,</hi> was gone himſelfe to <hi>Nice,</hi> which did cauſe him for to iudge, that the ſaide <hi>Sonnes,</hi> béeing nowe ſtrengthened with a newe ſupply of men, would aduenture and hazarde the bolder the combate. Whereunto the ſaide lorde deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to drawe and bring him, determined to batter <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiles,</hi> and to that ende brought foure Cannons from <hi>Ambrum,</hi> making them to paſſe the mountaines, and to be planted in ſight of the place, not ceaſing neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe to ſhewe himſelfe euery other day before <hi>Chamois,</hi> where the ſaide <hi>Sonnes</hi> was. Who being gréeued with his importunacie, lefte <hi>Chamois,</hi> and retired to <hi>Suze,</hi> where the ſaide lorde <hi>Deguiſiers</hi> following him the ſixe and twentith day of September, to view the place and to marke the countenaunce of his ennemy, encountred him by chaunce not farre from <hi>Ialaſle,</hi> and halfe a league from <hi>Suze,</hi> accompanyed with fiftéene hundrethe harque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buziers, and fiue cornets of horſemen, whome he aſſaul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſo furiouſly at the entring of the plaine, that the enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my being charged with one hundred and thrée ſcore horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, was diſcomfited and put to flight, leauing foure hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred launciers dead vppon the place. Amongeſt whome were <hi>Clapot</hi> the elder, ſergeant of the battaile, the lorde <hi>Montaignes</hi> and <hi>Valuernes.</hi> There were ſeauentéene head Captaines or chiefe officers ſlaine and taken. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15707:9"/>the priſoners was <hi>Clapot</hi> the yonger Mariſhal or the campe, who alſo dyed two dayes after, <hi>Labras</hi> lieue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant of the Marqueſſe of <hi>Traforts</hi> cornet, the gouernour of <hi>Breſche,</hi> Captaine <hi>Triſolts</hi> of <hi>Sauoy,</hi> Captaine de la <hi>Riuier,</hi> and the Captaine S. <hi>Orens.</hi> And if they had not retired in time, not one ſhoulde haue eſcapes. As touching the Generall <hi>Sonnes,</hi> he was loſt, in ſo much, that his men ſuppoſed him to be ſlaine till about midnight, that he came before the gates of <hi>Sauze.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The day before being the fiue and twentith day, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on aduice that the ennemy ſhoulde make a courſe in <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallo Monſieur</hi> de <hi>Briquemault</hi> was ſent thither, and arriued in good tyme with his cornet of light horſemen, and founde the ennemy vppon his retire, of whome hie caught a dozen.</p>
            <p>The ſeuen and twentith day the lord <hi>Diguiſiers</hi> fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding hunſelfe renforced by thoſe of <hi>Ponts</hi> and <hi>Briancon,</hi> who had ſent vnto him two hundred Souloiours as well of their troupes as of the goueruours, and S. <hi>Sauuois</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panies, and two or thrée hundred ſhot, chaunged and alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red wholy his purpoſe vpon <hi>Eſſiles,</hi> which beganne alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to parlée.</p>
            <p>The reſt of that moneth was ſpent in the ſéege of <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiles,</hi> whereof the gouernour called <hi>Ponſonnes,</hi> and was there by the Duke de <hi>Maines</hi> appointment, ſéeing the ill eſtate of the Duke of <hi>Sauoys</hi> affaires, the Cannon plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, the lorde <hi>Diguiſiers</hi> fortified with newe ſupplies, all
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15707:9"/>the communatty bent againſt him, and no likelſhoode of any aide and reléefe, yéelded at laſt the towne vpon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, that all the Souldiors ſhoulde fréely departe with bagge and baggage, which happened the laſt day of September. And by theſe meanes the paſſage of the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines remained in the Kings power. And <hi>Daulphine</hi> was limited with his olde limites, long bofore fortified by the French Kings during the warres of <hi>Italie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nerte day after this yéewing, the lorde <hi>Diguiſiers</hi> hauing vnderſtoode, that <hi>Monſieur Morges</hi> his nephewe had aſſigned a day to fight fiftie againſt fiftre on horſe backe with Generall <hi>Sonnes,</hi> conducted his nephew vnto the place appointed, where hée remained with his forces from nine of the clocke in the morning, vntill thrée of the clacke in the afternoone, without any appearaunce of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenay, but by a Trumpetter, who brought a letter from <hi>Sonnes,</hi> the contentes where of were, that vppon the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he had taken, he thad demaunrded the Infant her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> had as yet receiued no anſwere.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſame day being the firſt day of October, the lorde <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in attending the comming of his ennemie, had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> paſſage neare <hi>Iallon,</hi> where the enemy had intren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed hunſelfe, and lodged eight companies of Infanterie, vnder the leading and conduct of the Generall <hi>Venuſt,</hi> and perceining by the ſaws <hi>Sonnes</hi> anſwere, that there was no more hope of the combate, determined to ſpend the reſt of the day in aſſaulting the ſaide place, lying vpon the hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the mountaine, betwéene <hi>Suze</hi> and <hi>Noualiſe.</hi> And hauing found meanes to lodge and place a hundreth Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quettiers,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:15707:10"/>who battered the enemy vpon the ſide of theſt Skonſe, their treuches were forced, and foure ſcore of them ſlaine, but he reſt ſaued themſelues by their ſwiftencſſe. The ſaide <hi>Venuſt,</hi> Captaine <hi>Caſſard,</hi> and <hi>Charband,</hi> were ſlaine vpon the place, the Captaine <hi>Villars,</hi> and ſome other taken priſoners, undfoure commpanies of <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> Maiſter of the campe were ſo ſcattered, that they cams not ſince together.</p>
            <p>From thence the ſaide lorde <hi>Diguiſiers</hi> reinrned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to <hi>Eſsiles,</hi> and ſent backe againe the foure cannens to <hi>Ambrmn,</hi> cauſing at the ſame time two orrat péecrs to be drawen from <hi>Gap</hi> to <hi>Barcellona,</hi> a place belenging vnto the Doke, and ſrituated in the Countie of <hi>Nice,</hi> the which being befieged with his forces whom he had ſent before, at his arriual with the Canons, battered the towne the Satterday following, And vpon the ſame day a breach being made, the enemy did parlec, and yéelded themſelues, their liues ſaued, vnto hun, leauing neuertheleſſe their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, colours, horſes, and baggage behinde them: except the Captaines who were permitted to departe with their Swordes vpon a backney. Vnto the inhabitants was graunted the enjoying of their goodes, abiding vnder the Kings obedience, as all ſubiects of his Maieſtie, vpon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition alſo to pay fire thouſand crownes for the army and fraight of the artifllerie. The Gouernour called <hi>Core<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loere,</hi> departed from thence the fouretéenth day with thrée other forraine Soiddiors, and with as many Citizens and Countriemen, who went to their houſes vnder the Kings ſafegarde.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:15707:10"/>
            <p> The foureteenth day, the ſaooe lorde laſde batterie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Caſtell of <hi>Metans,</hi> which be battered but flender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ths fifteenth day, onely to viewe the ennemies rounte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naimee, who (being afraide of the cannon ſhot) nexte night ſaued themſelues, except thirtie of them that were faken priſoners by the watch. Here is the ſummarie of that which to paſſed in the beginning of this warre, where the lorde <hi>Diguiſires</hi> had neuer aboue thrée hundred horſes and twelue hundred ſhot, hauing alſo no greater ennemy then the inacceſſible height of the mountaines, where he was forced to paſſe his cannons, and chiefly in his fourhey to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes <hi>Barcellona.</hi> But care and daligence did nuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all difficulties. The praiſe whereof be giuen to God. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:15707:11"/>
            <head>A Godly Praier and Thankeſ-gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing <hi>vnto GOD, for his wonderfull</hi> mercies, in preſeruing and maintening the defendors of the truth, and diſcomforting of the enemies of the ſame.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Heauenly father, the Creator of all creatures, the ſtrength of all armies, the King of all kings, and the worker of all wonders, we thy diſtreſſed ſeruants do humbly beſeech thee to looke downe vpon vs from the throne of thy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Maieſtie, and for thy mercies ſake to take compaſsion on vs. We acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge (O Lorde) that our inſolent actions, togither with our pride and wickednes of life, hath wel deſerued thy wrath and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy diſpleaſure, ſo that the continuance of thy wrath theſe many yeares vppon thy Church, hath been no more then we haue iuſtly deſerued. Neuertheleſſe (heauenly Father) we preſume vpon thy ſtrength, and the multitude of thy mercies, &amp; that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:15707:11"/>thou wilt ſaue and defend all thoſe that ſeeke to ſupporte the trueth. Let not thy heart be hardened againſt vs (O Lord) for thou art our father, ſauiour, and redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning. We haue (O Lord) erred from thy wayes, and contrariwiſe, we haue hardned our hearts againſt thee: for which nowe we remaine ſorrowfull. Notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding let the inward ſorrowes of our hearts (O Lorde) be an occaſion to withdrawe thy wrath and heauy diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure from vs, which bringeth no other then bloudſhed, death and deſtruction vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our ſelues. Our enemies (Lorde) haue long ſought to triumph ouer vs, and haue greeuouſly ſpoyled thy holy Temples, yea they haue made hauocke of thy creatures, and haue ſo little regarded vs, as though thou hadſt neuer beene Lorde ouer vs, yea as though thy glorious Name had neuer beene called on by vs (O Lord) we beſeech thee for thy mercie ſake, let the malitious minds of thoſe which ſeeke daily our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, boyle away as the water doth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15707:12"/>on the fire, that thy mightines may be tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly knowne to thy enemies, and that they may tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble at thy wonderfull works. Remember (O Father) that we are to thee as clay in the Potters handes, wee are the works of thy fingers, we are thy creatures, and therfore deliuer vs (O Lord) from this continual tribulation, where Syon is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in to a deſart, and Ieruſalem into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual deſolation. The places of holy prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er wherein our forefathers haue heretofore ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded forth thy glory, are now turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to heaps of fire, and continuall harbors for armed men, and ourland brought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, and the ground made like to a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dernes. Withdraw therefore (O heauenlie Father) the rod of thy wrath from vs, and thruſt foorth thy merciful hand for our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe. Thou haſt lately giuen to vs a taſte of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort in this, that thy capitall enemy now liuing is retired, and by thy power co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to fly from among vs, whom he inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with his mighty armies, great looks and politike deuices, who notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15707:12"/>the wonderfull reportes of his mightines durſt not hazard his quarrel vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a pitched field with vs, although his forces were three to one. To thee therefore (O Lorde) we render all thankes, and humbly giue praiſe to thy heauenly Maieſty for ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing vs ſome comfort, by daunting our enemies, which had it not bin for thy our ſtretched arme (O Lord) we had remained in great daunger, nay, we had bin troden vnder foot like chaffe, and made foode for the foules of the aire. But thou haſt beene our defendor and onely comfort, thou haſt ſtrengthned vs that were but weake, and weakned them which in ſhewe are verie ſtrong. Continue, we beſeech thee, this thy goodneſſe to vs for thy mercy ſake, bleſſe our friends and welwillers: comforte our diſtreſſed eſtate, and ſuffer not our enemies to preuaile againſt vs: giue vs grace (O Lord) dayly to indeuour our ſelues to laud and magnifie the holy name of thee, who liueſt and raigneſt worlde without ende, Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS:</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
